Moon Journal Records, 1995-2015
Sophia Smith Collection
Moon Journal Records
1995-2015
1995-2009
Moon Journal
764
3 (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Moon Journal, formerly Prarie Moon ReadOut!, grew out of monthly poetry readings at the Prarie Moon Feminist Books and Women Friendly Space in Arlington Heights, Illinois. This collection is comprised of periodicals and chapbooks published by Moon Journal Press, as well as "herstorical" material, ephemera, and photographs.
Historical Note
Founded in 1992, Prairie Moon Feminist Books and Women Friendly Space in Arlington Heights, Illinois, hosted two monthly readings: a poetry reading and an all-genre reading. Both were open to the public. In order to share the work presented there with a wider audience, founding co-editors Mary Ber and Jude Rittenhouse created a publication in 1995. This literary magazine was first called Prairie Moon ReadOut! (the name of the monthly all-genre readings) and soon renamed Moon Journal. The journal continued in publication for thirteen years with much help from the growing community of writers. Moon Journal Press was established in 2000 and published poetry, short story, and creative nonfiction chapbooks before ceasing operation in 2009.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Moon Journal Records consist of the periodicals and poetry, short story, and creative nonfiction chapbooks published by Moon Journal Press, plus a small amount of "herstorical" material, ephemera, and photographs dating from 1995 to 2015.
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Moon Journal founding co-editor Jude Rittenhouse donated the Records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2015.
Poets, American -- 20th century -- Sources; Feminism -- Periodicals; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Feminism in literature -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Feminist spirituality -- United States -- History -- Sources
- Moon Journal
  - The Herstory of Moon Journal, Artistic Statement of Purpose by Jude Rittenhouse, ephemera, and photographs, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Prairie Moon ReadOut! (Box 1)
    - Vol I, Issue 1Winter 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol I, Issue 2 and 3 Summer/Fall 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Moon Journal (Box 1)
    - Volume II, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Volume III, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Volume IV, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Volume V, 200-01 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Volume VI, 2001-02 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Volume VII, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Volume VIII, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Volume IX, 2004-05 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Volume X, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Volume XI-XII, 2006-07 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Volume XIII, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chapbooks published by Moon Journal Press
  - Blue Tissue Paper, Marjorie Zilen, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Everything is Foaming Up, Janet A. Baker, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - All the Women We Have Been, Kathleen West, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Slide Into Light, Shoshauna Shy, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - At Portage, Lynne Hume Burgess, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Gradual Day of My Mother's Dying, Paula Alida Roy, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Inhabiting the Body, Nina Corwin & Mary H. Ber, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Where Undulating Hills Meet, Helen Quade, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Shape of Grief, Mary Ber, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - A Place Beyond Luck, Jan Bottiglieri, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Season Passes, Beth Steele, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Slow Tear, Diana Smith, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - A Measure of Grace, Mary Boyle, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Archaeologist's Daughter, Kristy Bowen, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Debris, Elizabeth Marino, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Meeting the Grand Dame, Helen A. Quade & Joy Veaudry, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Old Man Walking, Almira Astudillo Gilles, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Universal, Kathy Kubik, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dancing with a Scorpion, Sharon Waller Knutson, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Of Birds and Birth, Helen A. Quade, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Selected Roles, Kathleen Kirk, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Suspended, Elizabeth Pessl-Rossi, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Emigre's Farewell Gathering, Nadia Rausch, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Stir of Seasons, Jerry Hauser, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Turning Point, Tabinda Bashir, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Thought Fish, Ruan Wright, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)